<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.0.1">Jekyll</generator>
<link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
<link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
<updated>2016-05-16T19:51:23-05:00</updated>
<id>/</id>
<title>FÄMÉ</title>
<subtitle>The Virtual Brain of Sir Edward Baird</subtitle>
<entry>
<title>Guidelines in Typography</title>
<link href="/guidelines-in-typography/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Guidelines in Typography" />
<published>2016-02-15T00:00:00-06:00</published>
<updated>2016-02-15T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
<id>/guidelines-in-typography</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="/guidelines-in-typography/">&lt;h2&gt;Just a few pointers from E.P.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No low x-heights (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?q=apercu+font&amp;amp;espv=2&amp;amp;biw=1019&amp;amp;bih=877&amp;amp;source=lnms&amp;amp;tbm=isch&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;sqi=2&amp;amp;ved=0ahUKEwjR1c2CzfrKAhXkmoMKHRNMCisQ_AUIBigB&quot;&gt;Apercu&lt;/a&gt; is a good example, while &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?q=apercu+font&amp;amp;espv=2&amp;amp;biw=1019&amp;amp;bih=877&amp;amp;source=lnms&amp;amp;tbm=isch&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;sqi=2&amp;amp;ved=0ahUKEwjR1c2CzfrKAhXkmoMKHRNMCisQ_AUIBigB#tbm=isch&amp;amp;q=futura+font&quot;&gt;Futura&lt;/a&gt; is not).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pair complementary typefaces (serif with sans serif not serif with serif).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aperatures (partially closed negative space), counters (closed negative space), and eyes (&amp;#39;e&amp;#39;) need to be large enough (&lt;a href=&quot;http://desktoppub.about.com/cs/typeanatomy/a/basic_anatomy.htm&quot;&gt;eyes vs. counters&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look out for serifs, links (connecting bit &amp;#39;g&amp;#39;), ears (&amp;#39;g&amp;#39; and &amp;#39;n&amp;#39; tabs), and spurs (pointy bits on letters &amp;#39;G&amp;#39;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AVOID Helvetica, especially Neue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
<summary>Just a few pointers from E.P.</summary>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Design Notes: E. Park</title>
<link href="/design-notes-2-e-park/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Design Notes: E. Park" />
<published>2016-01-27T00:00:00-06:00</published>
<updated>2016-01-27T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
<id>/design-notes-2-e-park</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="/design-notes-2-e-park/">&lt;h2&gt;The Space of Creation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Preferances do not rigidize the world. There are many dynamic meanings. How does my vision make me blind to the world? Optimizing via template and standardizing through usability sound not by the end all goal. How do actions carry emotional weight? What connectedness do the technology and the user consititute?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ex: infinite scrolling relates to the continuity of art making itself. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;!ALERT! If there are affordances of design that relate to infinity, how will or should they be perceived?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Differentiation and experimentation can free you. It&amp;#39;s not about what can or will be, its about what will never be (or never thought of: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OS0Tg0IjCp4&quot;&gt;Marina and Ulay&lt;/a&gt;). Catching the unobtainable, the good&amp;#39; ol HP hustle for dat snitch. In a way, it&amp;#39;s that surprise HP and the crowd has when the unbelievable happens--unpredicted surprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a space, you can leave enough room for unplanned moments. Are these always simply constructed spaces? Where the laws and regulations loosen their grasp on the wheel? With Marina, the atmosphere was broad, the chaos surging, and with not control something happened--emotion. In this case, a simple control scheme didn&amp;#39;t constrain the possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Design is much more than a science, it is a craft. The creative process can&amp;#39;t always thrive within global methodologies and formulas. Feel the process and build the tools of the craft.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
<summary>The Space of Creation</summary>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Art of Conversation</title>
<link href="/art-of-conversation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Art of Conversation" />
<published>2016-01-25T00:00:00-06:00</published>
<updated>2016-01-25T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
<id>/art-of-conversation</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="/art-of-conversation/">&lt;h2&gt;During a conversation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During a great debate/convo w my Sig, I got reprimanded for the way I went about talking. My tactic was to keep reiventing my argument&amp;#39;s words and test the theories I was placing forth. I prefer, or am maybe use to the other person adopting the same strategy as myself. In this way, both parties keep thinking about their stance and how evidence or arguments support it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, my Sig did not mirror my stance and felt put off. Siggy recommended to echo back and reword what I was hearing. Siggy appreciated investigating the argument this way and felt more involved in the convo. As a great positive consequence from helping push the opposing view and interweave both parties&amp;#39; ideas, I was able to elaborate and disover from a new perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
<summary>During a conversation</summary>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Design Notes: E. Park</title>
<link href="/design-notes-e-park/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Design Notes: E. Park" />
<published>2016-01-22T00:00:00-06:00</published>
<updated>2016-01-22T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
<id>/design-notes-e-park</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="/design-notes-e-park/">&lt;h2&gt;Transparency&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you are using a design, you look through the design while using it. There isn&amp;#39;t a thought process to use the item, but it is natural. The design is transparent, your design is not invading the user&amp;#39;s ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine a wine glass. When filled, it&amp;#39;s about the wine inside. The glass becomes out of focus. Its design does not impact the concept of the wine. Yet, when empty, the glass stands by itself: an object of beauty. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A balance between appearance and disappearance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Park: The web is a framework to a different experience. Is it worth having?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
<summary>Transparency</summary>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Chest &amp;#39;O Tech</title>
<link href="/chest-o-tech/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chest &#39;O Tech" />
<published>2016-01-19T00:00:00-06:00</published>
<updated>2016-01-19T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
<id>/chest-o-tech</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="/chest-o-tech/">&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.olyware.mathlock&amp;amp;hl=en&quot;&gt;Hiq Lockscreen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I could make a cool mod of this for other useful data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yo_(app)&quot;&gt;Yo app&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes really basic programs can have business applications. Try to think how you could streamline other products into business models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://docentedu.com/&quot;&gt;DocentEDU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What a gem! This is a really neat concept. Would my Noto share any features? How does their method differ from how I&amp;#39;d capture and arrange information?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.okeebo.com/demo/&quot;&gt;Okeebo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another diamond in the rough! An expandable book UI tree for literature. More information simply expands on demand. You can also make other connections that are only supported by virtual thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.diigo.com/&quot;&gt;Diigo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another project related to Docent. Can I use this service as a backend for Noto? Or should I try to learn their implementation and fabricate my own tools?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nudgeeducation.com/&quot;&gt;Nudge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A collection of browser teacher tools design for classroom utility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Web APIs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.ionic.io/what-is-cordova-phonegap/&quot;&gt;Basic terminology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mongodb.com/what-is-mongodb&quot;&gt;MongoDB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
<summary>Hiq LockscreenI think I could make a cool mod of this for other useful data.</summary>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Direct Manipulation Animation</title>
<link href="/direct-manipulation-animation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Direct Manipulation Animation" />
<published>2016-01-18T00:00:00-06:00</published>
<updated>2016-01-18T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
<id>/direct-manipulation-animation</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="/direct-manipulation-animation/">&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.91.6228&amp;amp;rep=rep1&amp;amp;type=pdf&quot;&gt;Research by M. Chan &amp;amp; J. Black 2006&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Issue: When forming mental models of systems, how do you support learner&amp;#39;s understandings of structure, purpose and functional relations among system entities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can a specialized version of animation provide a superior pathway to knowledge acquistion?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Purpose of Research&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examine presentation formats -- narrative, image/visual, and animation to discover differences in learning systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Secondary Goal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Show that text, visuals, and animation in a cohesive setup ultimately promotes superior learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Leads&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Visuals aid printed word learning (Larkin &amp;amp; Simon, 1987; Mayer &amp;amp; Gallini, 1990; Tversky, 1995).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complex interactivity and content can overburden learner&amp;#39;s cognitive resources (Sweller et al., 1996).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Revisit and review the 3 pathways of learning and discussion on haptic learning consequences (above Fig. 1).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Key Term&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Direct-manipulation animation (DMA) allows direct interaction (e.g., sliders and buttons), which contrains viewing direction, content pacing, and system parameter relationships (Chan &amp;amp; Black, 2006). DMA in this study specifically pertains to the haptic learning pathway (see lead 3). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Method&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Middle school students learning Newtonian mechanics (energy conversion and law of conversion of energy) in three conditions. Learners were given a pretest, retention test (written summary and diagram), &amp;quot;what-if&amp;quot; test (thought experiment: explain and predict), near-transfer task (apply learning to problem-solving tasks), and a far-transfer task (apply learning in novel situation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Conditions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Text based format (narrative).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Text and visual format.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Text and animation (DMA).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The format of the learning significantly predicted performance. Format had an above medium &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.uccs.edu/lbecker/effect-size.html&quot;&gt;effect size&lt;/a&gt; of .68. So DMA provided the best learning situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;As content became more complex, DMA improved performance in learner comphrension, what-if reasoning, problem-solving, and tranfser problems (Chan &amp;amp; Black, 2006).&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, DMA fosters concurrent sensorimotor feedback while investigating causal interactions and functional relations in the system of interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, understanding functional relationships (parameter changes interacting with other parameters) is of prime importance when building effective mental models. The DMA condition, involving learning haptically, gave learners an advantage to reasoning and perfroming.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
<summary>Research by M. Chan &amp;amp; J. Black 2006</summary>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Illusions</title>
<link href="/illusions/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Illusions" />
<published>2016-01-12T00:00:00-06:00</published>
<updated>2016-01-12T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
<id>/illusions</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="/illusions/">&lt;h2&gt;Typing Game &amp;amp;&amp;amp; Space Invaders&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other day I came across a &lt;a href=&quot;http://madewith.unity.com/stories/finding-voice-epistory-1&quot;&gt;video on twitter&lt;/a&gt; and I thought I had discovered gold! In this video, there was a game made with Unity3D where you could type words and then destroy approaching enemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;%7B%7Bsite.baseurl%7D%7D/images/Epistory.png&quot; alt=&quot;Epistory gameplay&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year I disovered a similar game called &lt;a href=&quot;http://zty.pe/&quot;&gt;ZType&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;%7B%7Bsite.baseurl%7D%7D/images/ZType.png&quot; alt=&quot;ZType.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the twitter game didn&amp;#39;t exactly meet my expectations, it was completely different from ZType, I enjoyed reading the article about Epistory and the challenge of the game&amp;#39;s story design.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
<summary>Typing Game &amp;amp;&amp;amp; Space Invaders</summary>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Test or Study 2 Learn?</title>
<link href="/test-or-study-2-learn/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Test or Study 2 Learn?" />
<published>2016-01-10T00:00:00-06:00</published>
<updated>2016-01-10T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
<id>/test-or-study-2-learn</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="/test-or-study-2-learn/">&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://public.wsu.edu/%7Efournier/Teaching/psych592/Readings/Karpicke_et_al_2008.pdf&quot;&gt;Research by J. Karpicke &amp;amp; H Roediger, 2008&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contemporary view: tests are traditionally seen as a pure and neutral assessment of knowledge (Karpicke &amp;amp; Roediger, 2008)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What consequences does the act of testing knowledge have on learning?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Purpose of research&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examine the effects of studying and testing on learning and long-term retention. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Secondary goal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assess students perspective on their learning outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Method&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Repeatedly study, then test items. Three drop conditions for successfully recalled items. One control condition. All learners then completed a final test one week later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Conditions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 All items studied and tested (control)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 Dropped from study but still tested&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 Dropped from test but still studied&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 Dropped from test and study&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were no differences between condition recall immediately after the learning phase. All learners had equal recall of the items. All learners also perceived that they would perfrom equally well during the final week delayed test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Testing items, rather than studying them, played an integral factor in preserving long-term knowledge (Karpicke &amp;amp; Roediger, 2008).&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Repeatedly studying items successfully recalled had no performance effect on the final week delayed test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the control (1) and still tested (2) conditions, learners recalled 80% (x̅) of the items.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Opposingly in the still studied (3) and completed item removal (4) conditions, learners recalled 36% (x̅) and 33% (x̅), respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Repeatedly test knowledge in order to promote long-term retrieval capability.&lt;/h3&gt;
</content>
<summary>Research by J. Karpicke &amp;amp; H Roediger, 2008</summary>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Google&amp;#39;s Ludwig Game</title>
<link href="/google-s-ludwig-game/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Google&#39;s Ludwig Game" />
<published>2016-01-07T00:00:00-06:00</published>
<updated>2016-01-07T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
<id>/google-s-ludwig-game</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="/google-s-ludwig-game/">&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/doodles/celebrating-ludwig-van-beethovens-245th-year&quot;&gt;The Musical Ludwig Game&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love the artwork of this simple logo-game. I think the artwork is actually made of paper scenes? And if it isn&amp;#39;t &amp;quot;real,&amp;quot; then it should have been. I like when designers pull in real world environments for their games. The added layer of depth grabs my attention and my actions feel more connected to that virtual space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are two more examples of the technique. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=btpeCVRslFM&quot;&gt;Lumino City&lt;/a&gt;; this is how they &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JO6t6H19CUk&quot;&gt;built that world&lt;/a&gt;, and an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rockpapershotgun.com/2014/11/06/making-of-lumino-city/&quot;&gt;interview about the process&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=U-hnhkrlqu0&quot;&gt;The Swapper&lt;/a&gt;, and a small &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.npr.org/sections/alltechconsidered/2013/11/13/245080686/in-space-no-one-can-hear-you-swap&quot;&gt;write up about the title&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
<summary>The Musical Ludwig Game</summary>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>UX UI Nick Rosencranz</title>
<link href="/ux-ui-nick-rosencranz/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="UX UI Nick Rosencranz" />
<published>2016-01-06T00:00:00-06:00</published>
<updated>2016-01-06T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
<id>/ux-ui-nick-rosencranz</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="/ux-ui-nick-rosencranz/">&lt;h2&gt;Notes from my meeting with NR&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Content Strategy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A plannful approach to examine what we do online. We&amp;#39;ll look at the words we use, the consistency across content, and generally how people go through the experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Business of Interest&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://braintraffic.com/&quot;&gt;Braintraffic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Enterprise Architecture&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a process of looking at tools that are cool but might be unfeasible in deployment. E.g., using snapchat as a student resource at UMN. The issue is that snapchat wouldn&amp;#39;t be able to handle financial aide. This works examines adoption rates, use across many devices, where a service can be used from, and having power to limit the unreasonable projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Community UX UI Resources&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://uxreactions.com/&quot;&gt;UX Reactions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.uxmatters.com/&quot;&gt;UX Matters&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://uxmastery.com/&quot;&gt;UX Mastery&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://userfocus.co.uk/&quot;&gt;USERFOCUS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.experientia.com/&quot;&gt;Putting People First&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://boxesandarrows.com/&quot;&gt;Boxes and Arrows&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be mindful to check for Twin Cities groups (e.g., IDGC)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out RSS readers. NR was running his own server [fever].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;The shoemaker&amp;#39;s kids do not where shoes.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Software considerations: How will it act as services degrade? Think about time, battery life, wifi data limitations. Think of the robustness of the product or service.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
<summary>Notes from my meeting with NRContent StrategyA plannful approach to examine what we do online. We&amp;#39;ll look at the words we use, the consistency across content, and generally how people go through the experience.</summary>
</entry>
</feed>
